# Fanyi Xiao

CONTACT Information 2078 Academic Surge University of California, Davis Davis, CA 95616, USA

Mobile: 949-491-2293 E-mail: fyxiao@ucdavis.edu

WWW: fanyix.cs.ucdavis.edu

RESEARCH INTERESTS I am broadly interested in computer vision and machine learning, with a focus on developing models to learn from videos. At a high level, my research interests can be categorized into three aspects: (i) Learning to understand videos. This includes developing algorithms for video recognition/detection/segmentation. (ii) Learning video representations with minimal human supervision (weakly and self-supervised learning from videos). (iii) Learning across modalities (e.g., image, video, language and audio).

### **EDUCATION**

# University of California Davis, Computer Science Dept., Davis, CA, USA

Ph.D., Computer Science, 2020

- Advisor: Prof. Yong Jae Lee
- Thesis: Multimodal Learning with Minimal Human Supervision from Videos and Natural Language

# Carnegie Mellon University, Robotics Institute, Pittsburgh, PA, USA

M.S., Robotics, 2014

- Advisors: Prof. Martial Hebert and Prof. Yaser Sheikh
- Thesis: Model Recommendation for Large Scale Exemplar-based Object Detection

## Central South University, Computer Science Department, Changsha, China

B.S., Computer Science, 2012

• Thesis: Facial Expression Analysis with Active Appearance Model

### Publications

- Haotian Liu, Rafael A. Rivera-Soto, Fanyi Xiao, and Yong Jae Lee. YolactEdge: Real-time Instance Segmentation on the Edge. In *International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)*, 2021.
- [2] Xueyan Zou, Fanyi Xiao, Zhiding Yu, and Yong Jae Lee. Delving Deeper into Anti-aliasing in ConvNets. In British Machine Vision Conference (BMVC), 2020. Best Paper Award.
- [3] Fanyi Xiao, Yong Jae Lee, Kristen Grauman, Jitendra Malik, and Christoph Feichtenhofer. Audiovisual SlowFast Networks for Video Recognition. arXiv preprint arXiv:2001.08740, 2020.
- [4] Daniel Bolya, Chong Zhou, Fanyi Xiao, and Yong Jae Lee. YOLACT++: Better Real-time Instance Segmentation. *IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (T-PAMI)*, 2020.
- [5] Fanyi Xiao, Haotian Liu, and Yong Jae Lee. Identity from here, Pose from there: Self-supervised Disentanglement and Generation of Objects using Unlabeled Videos. In *International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV)*, 2019.
- [6] Daniel Bolya, Chong Zhou, Fanyi Xiao, and Yong Jae Lee. YOLACT: Real-time Instance Segmentation. In International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV), 2019. Oral presentation.
- [7] Xitong Yang, Xiaodong Yang, Ming-Yu Liu, Fanyi Xiao, Larry S Davis, and Jan Kautz. STEP: Spatio-Temporal Progressive Learning for Video Action Detection. In Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR), 2019.

- [8] Fanyi Xiao and Yong Jae Lee. Video Object Detection with an Aligned Spatial-Temporal Memory. In European Conference on Computer Vision (ECCV), 2018.
- [9] Wenjian Hu, Krishna Kumar Singh\*, Fanyi Xiao\*, Jinyoung Han, Chen-Nee Chuah, and Yong Jae Lee (\* equal contribution). Who Will Share My Image? Predicting the Content Diffusion Path in Online Social Networks. In ACM International Conference on Web Search and Data Mining (WSDM), 2018.
- [10] Fanyi Xiao, Leonid Sigal, and Yong Jae Lee. Weakly-supervised Visual Grounding of Phrases with Linguistic Structures. In Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR), 2017.
- [11] **Fanyi Xiao** and Yong Jae Lee. Track and Segment: An Iterative Unsupervised Approach for Video Object Proposals. In *Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition* (CVPR), 2016. **Spotlight presentation**.
- [12] Krishna Singh, **Fanyi Xiao**, and Yong Jae Lee. Track and Transfer: Watching Videos to Simulate Strong Human Supervision for Weakly-Supervised Object Detection. In *Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)*, 2016.
- [13] Fanyi Xiao and Yong Jae Lee. Discovering the Spatial Extent of Relative Attributes. In *International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV)*, 2015. Oral presentation.
- [14] Fanyi Xiao and Martial Hebert. Efficient Model Evaluation with Bilinear Separation Model. In Winter Conference on Applications of Computer Vision (WACV), 2015.
- [15] Zhiding Yu, Chunjing Xu, Deyu Meng, **Fanyi Xiao**, Wenbo Liu, and Jianzhuang Liu. Transitive Distance Clustering with K-Means Duality. In *International Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)*, 2014.
- [16] Iljoo Baek, Taylor Stine, Denver Dash, Fanyi Xiao, Yaser Ajmal Sheikh, Yair Movshovitz-Attias, Mei Chen, Martial Hebert, and Takeo Kanade. Physical Querying with Multi-Modal Sensing. In Winter Conference on Applications of Computer Vision (WACV), 2014.

### AWARDS

- Best Paper Award, British Machine Vision Conference (BMVC), 2020
- Outstanding Reviewer, European Conference on Computer Vision (ECCV), 2020
- Most Innovative Award, COCO Object Detection Challenge, 2019
- Google Cloud Platform Research Grant, 2019
- Best Graduate Researcher Award, CS Dept. of UC Davis, 2018
- Azure Research Award, Microsoft, 2017
- Graduate Fellowship, UC Davis, 2015
- AWS Research Grant, Amazon Web Services, Inc., 2015
- Excellent Undergraduate Thesis, CSU, 2012
- Top Grade Scholarship (University-wide highest honor, 0.8%), CSU, 2010
- Sunward Scholarship (0.4%), Sunward Corporation, 2010
- 1st Grade Scholarship (6%), CSU, 2009
- National Scholarship (1%), Ministry of Education of China, 2009

#### EXPERIENCE

### Amazon AI, Seattle, WA

# Applied Scientist II

Aug 2020 - Present

- Conduct cutting-edge research on self-supervised video representation learning.
- Build computer vision solution to understand Media & Entertainment content.

## Facebook AI Research (FAIR), Menlo Park, CA

Research Intern

June 2019 - Nov 2019

• An audiovisual video understanding architecture for recognition, detection and multi-modal self-supervised video representation learning.

## NVIDIA Research, Santa Clara, CA

Research Intern

July 2017 - Oct 2017

• An iterative action tube detection method for action detection.

## Disney Research, Pittsburgh, PA

Research Intern

June 2016 - Sept 2016

• Weakly supervised vision-language alignment (i.e., producing segmentation masks for free-form language inputs) by exploiting linguistic structure.

SKILLS

- Programming: Python, C/C++, Lua, MATLAB, Java
- Misc: PyTorch, Torch7, Caffe, Caffe2, Linux, LATEX

RELATED GRADUATE COURSES

- CMU: Computer Vision / Machine Learning / Convex Optimization Math Fundamentals for Robotics / Learning-based Methods in Vision Mechanics of Manipulation
- UC Davis: Visual Recognition

Mentoring

- Daniel Bolya, undergraduate student (now PhD at Georgia Tech)
- Haotian Liu, undergraduate student (now PhD at UC Davis)
- Chong Zhou, MS student (now PhD at UNC Chapel Hill)
- Xueyan Zou, junior PhD student at UC Davis

SERVICE

- Reviewer, Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR), 2018-21
- Reviewer, International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV), 2019
- Reviewer, European Conference on Computer Vision (ECCV), 2020
- Reviewer, International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), 2021
- Reviewer, Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS), 2020
- $\bullet\,$  Program Committee, AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), 2019-20
- Program Committee, Intl. Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI), 2020
- Reviewer, The British Machine Vision Conference (BMVC), 2020
- Reviewer, Asian Conference on Computer Vision (ACCV), 2018
- Reviewer, Winter Conference on Applications of Computer Vision (WACV), 2015-18
- Reviewer, IEEE Transactions on Multimedia (TMM)